{
  "reference_number": "11684",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "This should only be changed in line with new international agreements backed up by scientific bodies (IPCC), or to speed up the\n target."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "It is urgent that emissions reduce particularly quickly in the first phase of emission reduction, not later."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "We are learning more all the time about causes & effects of climate change,. We don't know how effective the safeguards will be."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "As in Q1, only if targets are strengthened or backed by IPCC."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "5 years should be the maximum."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - each incoming Government should have the option to review the third budget in the sequence",
      "answer_index": 14,
      "notes": "But only if the Commission is in full agreement, & scientific research can improve target time."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "We are already in exceptional circumstances."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, on the 'how to' achieve targets. Not on the targets themselves, or the budgets for them."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "3 months max."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "These plans need specified implementation: responsibilities, timelines, accountabilities, consequences. They need teeth. No person\n\nor body responsible should be above liability."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Our recent history shows us that advice to government on the environment, even when sanctioned by government,(eg., from the\nParliamentary Commissioner for the Environment), can be ignored. The Commission needs to be appropriated sufficient resources to\nbe independent, & guaranteed access to MfE resources. The Bill needs to specify this."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": "The wording could be changed to \"NZ ETS or alternative methods.\" The reliance on the market using ETS is too much in doubt. It has\n\nnot worked in other sectors, eg., housing. Carbon budgets, or introducing carbon taxes, could be alternatives."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "But also, in international climate change, bio security, bio diversity, health, and social science."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Much more direction & compulsory implementation is required. Recent events have shown that many people need a catastrophe on\n\ntheir doorsteps, to realize the extent of change in the natural world. In our own area, I work as a landscape gardener, and am getting\nnumerous calls from residents in an area that was inundated in the storms earlier this year. The developer of this subdivision back in\n\nthe 1970's was refused consent the first two times he tried, but on his third try the council ignored their own predictions of future\ntrouble. Now the insurance companies are very busy there. (Thus escalating insurance costs to us all..)"
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "But the suggested tools 'A national climate Change Risk Assessment, 'the National adaption plan', & the 'National adaption reporting\npower' are positive examples of clarifying & strengthening the parameters."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Optimally this would be brought under the responsibility of the Commission itself, rather than another body."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "This Bill is the most important piece of legislation this year. It needs to be future government-proof. Thankyou for setting this Bill in\nmotion!"
    }
  ]
}
